<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Augusto Altenhofen</title><link href="altenhofen.github.io/blog" rel="alternate"/><id>altenhofen.github.io/blog</id><updated>2026-05-01T00:00:00Z</updated><subtitle>survival notes</subtitle><entry><title>Why you should pick open-source tools as a developer</title><link href="altenhofen.github.io/blog/setup" rel="alternate"/><published>2026-05-01T00:00:00Z</published><updated>2026-05-01T00:00:00Z</updated><id>tag:None,2026-05-01:altenhofen.github.io/blog/setup</id><summary type="html">

&lt;p&gt; Originally posted 2026-05-01&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Tagged: &lt;a href="/blog/tags/linux"&gt;linux&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="/blog/tags/setup"&gt;setup&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="/blog/tags/workstation"&gt;workstation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id="programming-a-craft"&gt;Programming, a craft&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve used several closed-source, proprietary tools for a long time as
a developer, but all of them left a bad taste in my mouth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I have to talk good things about proprietary software I’ve
used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve never encountered a problem on Windows that wouldn’t be solved
by a clean reinstall of the software, sure that meant messing around
with &lt;em&gt;Regedit&lt;/em&gt; and maybe hidden folders on &lt;em&gt;C:\Windows&lt;/em&gt;,
but it was never a HUGE problem, like the ones you find when debugging
Pulseaudio on Linux, for example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve never had bad UI/UX experiences with VSCode*. Or with the
JetBrains Debugger. The good part about proprietary software is that its
usability is generally more smooth for the base-case than open
source.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open-source, in my experience, can generally have ‘idiotic’ things.
Such as Linux’s major GUI not having thumbnails for the file picker
browser for over 20-something years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For long, I thought that the use of proprietary tools as a programmer
made more sense since they were made by professionals, and open source
for me was the eternal archetype of &lt;strong&gt;Richard Stallman playing
Super Tux Kart&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also would think that the same way that miners don’t (necessarily)
have the know-how to make a pickaxe, the programmer shouldn’t really
care about how and his tools are made, or care about the tools at
all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next sections, I’ll draft a general idea on why you should
consider caring about your tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-mindset-shift"&gt;The mindset shift&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First thing is, a pickaxe isn’t vendor locked. Also, the manufacturer
can’t really FORCE YOU NOT TO use a pickaxe by just removing some files
on a server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="visual-studio-for-mac"&gt;Visual Studio For Mac&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visual Studio for Mac suffered this fate. I’ve never used it, but its
a clear case of how companies can just press Shift+Del on a piece of
locked-in software. Nowadays, you can download the, already pretty
disgusting, web-installer, but all the files that were downloaded by the
installer were deleted by Microsoft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the people who relied on Microsoft’s software were now forced to
migrate to closed-source Rider (for C#) or other alternatives such as
VSCode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="windows-11"&gt;Windows 11&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Windows 11 broke the ‘Metro UI’ that was used by Microsoft since
Windows 8, which for some was a scandal. What if Microsoft just
arbitrarily changed the “disable mouse acceleration” button? What if
they forced an AI tool into it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve never seen this huge philosophy difference between open and
closed-source software, for me it was just a matter of public
development, licenses and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what made my mind shift: the free and open-source can live
forever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="built-to-last"&gt;Built to last&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Linus Torvalds uses the same version of uEmacs that he used in the
1990s. As long as you have the source code and the ability to tweak some
of the build process or dependencies, you can use the software basically
forever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not the company, nor the guy who wrote it, neither the ones who host
the source-code will lock you out of it. If I want to use, for some
reason, my neovim 0.10.0 on a very old Linux, or 20 years in the future,
why couldn’t I? I have the source code, and programming skills, that’s
enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s the beauty of open source, people are still building Firefox
for Windows 7 even though Mozilla has stopped the development, some
people still patch Rust, Firefox, Chromium to work on out-of-date
operating systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of using the same GUI &lt;strong&gt;forever&lt;/strong&gt; is pretty
common on Linux.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If for some reason you liked &lt;code&gt;wmii&lt;/code&gt;, you can just download
the source code, and possibly make some fixes for it to compile and
voilá. Or even better, someone could’ve already done it, and you can
just download the fork, or the PKGBUILD, whatever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="key-takeaways"&gt;Key takeaways&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tmux will last forever. Neovim will not get a random AI chat thingy
when I next open it. i3 will always create a new window on
Super+Return.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, if you want a more utilitarian argument:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;using the same portable open-source tools builds consistency, muscle
memory and it’s boring enough so you can focus on your work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should be able to install my tools on possibly every operating
system with UNIX utilities and a C compiler.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;1. VSCode as in the software released by Microsoft is
proprietary. You cannot reproduce the builds you download.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</summary></entry><entry><title>Now</title><link href="altenhofen.github.io/blog/now" rel="alternate"/><published>2026-03-01T00:00:00Z</published><updated>2026-03-01T00:00:00Z</updated><id>tag:None,2026-03-01:altenhofen.github.io/blog/now</id><summary type="html">

&lt;p&gt; Originally posted 2026-03-01&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Tagged: (None)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This page is inspired by &lt;a href="https://sive.rs"&gt;Derek Sivers&lt;/a&gt;.
See &lt;a href="https://nownownow.com"&gt;nownownow&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="january-2026"&gt;january 2026&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id="created-this-blog"&gt;created this blog&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4 id="got-a-new-job"&gt;got a new job&lt;/h4&gt;
</summary></entry><entry><title>Hello world</title><link href="altenhofen.github.io/blog/first" rel="alternate"/><published>2026-03-01T00:00:00Z</published><updated>2026-03-01T00:00:00Z</updated><id>tag:None,2026-03-01:altenhofen.github.io/blog/first</id><summary type="html">

&lt;p&gt; Originally posted 2026-03-01&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Tagged: &lt;a href="/blog/tags/hello"&gt;hello&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="/blog/tags/world"&gt;world&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the first post of this blog. :)&lt;/p&gt;
</summary></entry><entry><title>Quotes</title><link href="altenhofen.github.io/blog/quotes" rel="alternate"/><published>2026-01-01T00:00:00Z</published><updated>2026-01-01T00:00:00Z</updated><id>tag:None,2026-01-01:altenhofen.github.io/blog/quotes</id><summary type="html">

&lt;p&gt; Originally posted 2026-01-01&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Tagged: (None)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id="economics-state-and-freedom"&gt;Economics, State and Freedom&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The direct use of physical force is so poor a solution to the problem
of limited resources that it is commonly employed only by small children
and great nations. — David Friedman&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</summary></entry></feed>